<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Alternative-treatments | ALS | MND</title><link>/alternative-treatment/</link><atom:link href="/alternative-treatment/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Alternative-treatments</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>Alternative-treatments</title><link>/alternative-treatment/</link></image><item><title>Masitinib</title><link>/alternative-treatment/masitinib/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/masitinib/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Masitinib is an oral treatment designed to block the activity of multiple cell types — including macrophages, neutrophils, mast cells, and Schwann cells — involved in the inflammatory and neurodegenerative processes marking ALS. It does so through the activity of proteins called tyrosine kinases.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Check &lt;a href="https://www.ab-science.com/science/masitinib-in-neurodegenerative-disorders/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">AB Science&lt;/a> page to know more.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="2019---add-on-masitinib-slows-progression-of-als-final-phase-23-trial-results-showhttpswwwtandfonlinecomdoifull1010802167842120191632346">&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2019.1632346" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2019 - Add-on Masitinib Slows Progression of ALS, Final Phase 2/3 Trial Results Show&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./masitinib_as_an_add_on_therapy_to_riluzole_in_patients_with_als.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Masitinib in combination with Rilutek (riluzole) slows functional decline of patients with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) who have a typical disease progression, according to the final report of AB Science‘s Phase 2/3 clinical trial.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At 11 months of treatment with the combo, the rate of disability progression was reduced by 27%, as compared to a placebo plus Rilutek. In contrast, patients who have a faster disease worsening do not benefit as much from adding masitinib to their treatment.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="./masitinib_phaseII.png" alt="PhaseII results">&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>from &lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/news-posts/2020/04/03/fda-clears-ab-science-to-open-phase-3-trial-of-masitinib-add-on-als-treatment/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ALS News Today&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>Deanna Protocol</title><link>/alternative-treatment/deanna-protocol/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/deanna-protocol/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Protocols for ALS are mainly empirical (i.e based on personal experience),
so please be sure to always do your research and make your own mind.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="the-story-behind-the-protocol">The story behind the protocol&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In 2009, Deanna was a healthy 31-yr-old pregnant newlywed with plenty of energy, an active lifestyle, and a successful career as a trial attorney and a Partner in a Tampa law firm. Her life came to a halt, when she was diagnosed with ALS after she found herself falling and losing balance frequently. She sought help from the most credible physicians and institutions in the country in treating ALS and they all told her the same thing: “There is no cure. There is no effective way to manage the disease. Your disease is progressing quickly and you will be dead in 2 years.” They were right. Within months, she went from walking normally and running several miles a day to walking very slowly with a cane. She was dying…quickly. This is when Deanna’s father Dr. Tedone (MD) took action.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He began reading all scientific research on ALS in the past 100 years to try to find a solution for Deanna. Based on his medical knowledge and familiarity with ALS research, he began testing safe substances on Deanna and eventually teamed up with scientists at the University of South Florida to test and refine these substances in the lab. This is how the original Deanna Protocol was born. When on the Deanna Protocol, Deanna’s physical condition stopped deteriorating and she stabilized (which is unheard of in ALS patients who are progressing quickly). Deanna was doing so well on the Deanna Protocol that other ALS patients who knew her began asking Dr. Tedone to share information with them on what Deanna was taking. Others with ALS began seeing incredible results and began referring friends and writing about their improvements on ALS related blogs and websites. Word of mouth continued to spread and, now, there are over 6,000 individuals with ALS on the Deanna Protocol worldwide.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Throughout the years, Dr. Tedone and scientists at different universities have tested and improved upon the Protocol, which has given way to the Deanna Protocol that exists today: a patent pending substance with a proprietary ratio of &lt;strong>Arginine (AAKG)&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>Alpha-Ketoglutaric acid (AKG)&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>Gamma-Aminobutyric acid (GABA)&lt;/strong>. These are all substances that are naturally found in the body. However, people with ALS need more of these substances to give fuel to the Krebs Cycle (energy producing cycle) in their nerve cells, in order to keep their diseased nerve cells alive. Think of the Deanna Protocol as special fuel needed to keep the cell’s engine running when the engine is malfunctioning because of a disease.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find a lot more information on the official website: &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/">https://winningthefight.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-protocol">The protocol&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="supplements">Supplements&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="arginine-alpha-ketoglutarate-aakg">Arginine-alpha-ketoglutarate (AAKG)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="gamma-aminobutyric-acid-gaba">Gamma Aminobutyric Acid (GABA)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="optional-supplements">Optional Supplements&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="alpha-ketoglutarate-akg">Alpha-ketoglutarate (AKG)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="coenzyme-q10-coq10">Coenzyme Q10 (CoQ10)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dr-tedone-advices">Dr Tedone advices&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Take AAKG with a ration of 1:1 Arginine to Alpha-Ktoglutarate.&lt;br>
Example:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nz.iherb.com/pr/Primaforce-AAKG-Unflavored-250-g/58649" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Primaforce&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.simplesanutrition.com/products/aakg-powder-250-grams.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Simplesa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="borrelia-bacteria">Borrelia Bacteria&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We have a strong body of evidence suggesting that ALS is likely caused by an undiagnosed infection with borrelia bacteria and at times coinfections Deanna and the vast majority of other individuals we have worked with who have ALS have been diagnosed with borrelia infections &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Please check &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/borrelia-bacteria/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this page&lt;/a> with test recommendation&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Arginine-alpha-ketoglutarate (AAKG)
Delivers energy to nerves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Alpha-ketoglutarate (AKG)
Delivers energy to nerves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gamma Aminobutyric Acid (GABA)
Inhibitory neurotransmitter&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nicotinamide
Stops nerve cell death&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="2017---evaluation-of-holistic-treatment-for-als-reveals-possible-mechanism-and-therapeutic-potentialhttpswwwncbinlmnihgovpmcarticlespmc6326589">&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6326589/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2017 - Evaluation of Holistic Treatment for ALS Reveals Possible Mechanism and Therapeutic Potential&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./evaluation_of_holistic_treatment_for_als_reveals_possible_mechanism_and_therapeutic_potential.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In this study, glutamate exposure to human motoneurons was investigated and found not to significantly affect cell viability or electrophysiological properties. However, varicosities were observed in axons suggestive of transport impairment that was dose dependent for glutamate exposure. Surprisingly, a subset of the components of the DP eliminated these varicosities.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2014---metabolic-therapy-with-deanna-protocol-supplementation-delays-disease-progression-and-extends-survival-in-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-als-mouse-modelhttpswwwncbinlmnihgovpmcarticlespmc4111621">&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4111621/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2014 - Metabolic Therapy with Deanna Protocol Supplementation Delays Disease Progression and Extends Survival in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) Mouse Model&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./deanna_protocol_delay.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Our results support the idea that targeted metabolic therapies, like the DP, can improve motor function and survival time, though further research is needed to elucidate the cellular and molecular mechanisms underlying these results. Dose response studies, histological analysis, and metabolomic analysis will help to define the optimal formula to enhance metabolic substrate delivery and utilization to help mitigate the ALS pathology. The components of the DP supplement have a good safety profile and are readily available over the counter, which is an important consideration in moving this therapy into phase I clinical trial.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2013---als-untangled---deanna-protocolhttpswwwalsuntangledcomreviewdeanna-protocol">&lt;a href="https://www.alsuntangled.com/review/deanna-protocol/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2013 - ALS Untangled - Deanna Protocol&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./als_untangled_20_deanna_protocol.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Mitochondrial dysfunction, glutamate excitotoxicity, and oxidative stress have all been implicated in ALS pathogenesis, and targeting these mechanisms individually or by a cocktail such as the Deanna Protocol could play a role in future ALS therapies. However, many of the preclinical and animal studies related to these pathways have not translated into successful treatments in patients with ALS. While there are anecdotal reports of improvements in patients with ALS on the Deanna Protocol, there is no convincing objective evidence of benefit yet. Thus, at this time, ALSUntangled does not recommend the Deanna Protocol to patients with ALS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before it can be recommended, a reproducible version of the Deanna Protocol should be shown to influence plausible physiologic mechanisms such as central nervous system ketone bodies, as well as clinically meaningful outcome measures such as ALSFRS-R and FVC in patients with ALS.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>from &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">winningthefight.org&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/borrelia-bacteria/">https://winningthefight.org/borrelia-bacteria/&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>Melatonin</title><link>/alternative-treatment/melatonin/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/melatonin/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Melatonin is a naturally occurring hormone that is best known for its role in sleep regulation. After screening more than a thousand FDA-approved drugs several years ago, researchers determined that melatonin is a powerful antioxidant that blocks the release of enzymes that activate apoptosis, or programmed cell death.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dosage">Dosage&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;span>&lt;small>&lt;em>Those have been taken out of the articles for your convenience&lt;/em>&lt;/small>&lt;/span>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>300mg/day as suppository&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="2013---melatonin-slows-als-symptoms-in-micehttpswwwfuturityorgmelatonin-slows-als-symptoms-in-mice">&lt;a href="https://www.futurity.org/melatonin-slows-als-symptoms-in-mice/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2013 - Melatonin slows als symptoms in mice&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="2006---reduced-oxidative-damage-in-als-by-high-dose-enteral-melatonin-treatment">2006 - Reduced oxidative damage in ALS by high-dose enteral melatonin treatment&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./reduced_oxidative_damage_in_als_by_high.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>[&amp;hellip;] melatonin slowed disease progression by 25% or 73%, depending on the definition of &amp;ldquo;disease onset&amp;rdquo;, by the appearance of first tremor or failure on the rotarod, respectively.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Translating these findings to human ALS, we are aware that a cure by melatonin is unlikely. An increase in life expectancy, however, is a worth-while goal, specifically during the early stages of this disease.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description></item><item><title>Research - Seneca NSI-566</title><link>/alternative-treatment/nsi-566/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/nsi-566/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>NSI-566 is an investigational neural stem cell therapy that uses human spinal cord stem cells (HSSCs). Stem cells are unique in that they have the capacity to differentiate into many types of specialized cells during development.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When injected into the spinal cord, NSI-566 differentiates into types of neurons found in adults. They surround and support motor neurons damaged by ALS, by integrating into the neural network and forming connections (synapses) with the patient’s own neurons. They also secrete certain molecules that promote motor neuron growth and survival.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Seneca Bio received orphan designation by the FDA for NSI-566 in ALS. NSI-566 was evaluated in Phase 1 and Phase 2 safety studies in 30 patients. The data showed that the intraspinal transplantation of the cells was safe and well tolerated. Subjects from both the Phase 1 and Phase 2 studies continue to be monitored for long-term follow-up evaluations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can check Seneca &lt;a href="https://senecabio.com/pipeline/nsi-566.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">product pipeline&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="2020---als-news-today-nsi-566httpsalsnewstodaycomnsi-566">&lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/nsi-566/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 - ALS news today: NSI-566&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>When injected into the spinal cord, these fetal stem cells differentiate into the kind of neurons that exist in the adult body. They surround and support the impaired motor neurons in ALS by integrating into the neural network and forming connections (synapses) with the patient’s own neurons&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2020---als-news-today-seneca-is-now-moving-to-phase-iiihttpsalsnewstodaycom20200413potential-stem-cell-therapy-nsi-566-moving-into-phase-3-trial-seneca-says">&lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/2020/04/13/potential-stem-cell-therapy-nsi-566-moving-into-phase-3-trial-seneca-says/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 - ALS news today: Seneca is now moving to Phase III&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Seneca Biopharma announced that work is underway to advance NSI-566, its leading stem cell treatment candidate, into a Phase 3 study in people with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The decision followed a meeting with the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA), and is supported by data collected from a Phase 1 (NCT01348451) and Phase 2 (NCT01730716) clinical trial.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="new-data-recently-developed-from-the-p1p2-study-regarding-insights-into-potential-for-efficacyhttpssenecabiocomnews-mediapress-releasesdetail244neuralstem-announces-publication-of-long-term-follow-uphtml">&lt;a href="https://senecabio.com/news-media/press-releases/detail/244/neuralstem-announces-publication-of-long-term-follow-up.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New data recently developed from the P1/P2 study regarding insights into potential for efficacy&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./2018-05-03_Neuralstem_Announces_Publication_of_Long_Term_244.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Post-hoc comparison of combined cohorts from Phase 1 and 2 trials vs. historical controls revealed statistically significant
difference in scores in functional status and in a composite statistic combining survival and functional status in subjects receiving
human spinal cord-derived neural stem cells.&lt;br>
Study provides validation for additional trials to evaluate the benefit of neural stem cells in ALS patients&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2018---neuralstem-nsi-566-and-nsi-189httpswwwyoutubecomwatchvfbqhde0vnmat213s">&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fBQHDE0vnmA&amp;amp;t=213s" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2018 - Neuralstem NSI-566 and NSI-189&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
&lt;iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/fBQHDE0vnmA" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video">&lt;/iframe>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Acupuncture</title><link>/alternative-treatment/acupuncture/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/acupuncture/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Acupuncture has been used in traditional Chinese medicine for more than 2,000 years. It is based on Taoist philosophy, which suggests that good health depends on uninterrupted blood circulation through all the organs of the body and that disruption in circulation affects normal physiological function.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In acupuncture therapy, fine, sterile metal needles are inserted under the skin along specially designated points along the body called acupoints. This procedure is touted to stimulate the release of natural painkillers in the human body and affect areas in the brain that process pain.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most commonly used acupuncture techniques in ALS include scalp and spinal acupuncture where fine needles are inserted alongside the governing vessel, which runs up the spine to the head and over the center of the scalp.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In some cases, needle insertion is accompanied by the application of small electric currents (electroacupuncture) or injection of chemicals (acupuncture injection therapy).&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are no clinical trials currently testing the effects of acupuncture therapy for ALS specifically. Most of the information available about its potential benefits for ALS symptoms is from clinical case studies and Chinese literature.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="2017---amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-an-acupuncture-approach">2017 - Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis: An Acupuncture Approach&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./als_acupunture.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Although the motor dysfunctions are the main symptoms of ALS, spasticity and associated pain are common, and acupuncture has been shown in studies to be most useful for alleviating these symptoms.
Significant neurologic improvements in 2 patients with ALS after acupuncture injection therapy were reported by Liang et al.
There are other studies showing beneficial effects of acupuncture in ALS, involving motor functions, in Chinese literature that is not referenced in PubMed&lt;br>
One of these is by Cheng Yongde who treated 46 patients who had ALS with acupuncture and Chinese herbs and is detailed in an article by Dharmananda
Six patients had clinical remission; for 11, the treatment was markedly effective; for 24, it was fairly effective; and for 5, it was ineffective&lt;br>
The current case is remarkable in that, after relentless aggravation for 4 months resulting in Grade 2 weakness in both feet—which made climbing stairs impossible and caused considerable difficulty in walking even on level ground 2 months of acupuncture reversed most of this patient’s symptoms—spasm, pain, weakness and fasciculation—and she was able to climb stairs and engage in brisk walking for 2 hours every day. This could be labeled as a placebo effect, spontaneous resolution, or a doctor–patient relationship effect.&lt;br>
&lt;strong>No conclusion can be drawn from a single case; the emphasis here is on the approach to the patient&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="2015---a-modern-clinical-approach-of-the-traditional-korean-saam-acupuncture">2015 - A Modern Clinical Approach of the Traditional Korean Saam Acupuncture&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./a_modern_clinical_approach_traditional_korean_saam_acupuncture.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="2015---als-untangled---acupuncture">2015 - ALS Untangled - Acupuncture&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./alsuntangled_28_acupuncture.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Acupuncture is reasonably safe, and has potential mechanisms of action, pre-clinical studies and case reports suggesting that it could be a useful treatment for ALS. However, before it can be endorsed even as a candidate for a phase II trial, the studies described above need to be independently replicated using more clearly verified diagnoses and more rigorous designs, including appropriate controls and validated ALS outcome measures.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="2013---the-effects-of-sa-am-acupuncture-treatment-on-respiratory-physiology-parameters-in-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-patients-a-pilot-study">2013 - The Effects of Sa-Am Acupuncture Treatment on Respiratory Physiology Parameters in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis Patients: A Pilot Study&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./saam_acupuncture_treatment_on_respiratory_physiology.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="2011---significant-neurological-improvement-in-two-patients-with-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-after-4-weeks-of-treatment-with-acupuncture-injection-point-therapy-using-enercel">2011 - Significant Neurological Improvement in Two Patients with Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis After 4 Weeks of Treatment with Acupuncture Injection Point Therapy Using Enercel&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./acupuncture_injection_point_therapy_using_enercel.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Two patients with ALS were treated with 4 weeks of acupuncture injection therapy using Enercel. These individuals demonstrated significant improvements in speech and muscle strength in the extremities after treatment. The patients were regularly contacted for 3 months after receiving treatment.&lt;br>
Patient #1 did not maintain the Enercel acupoint injection treatments due to restrictions in her home state. She did not receive regular Enercel adminis- trations via oral, sublingual, or intramuscular routes. She demonstrated a slow decline in neurological functioning over the following 3 months, although at the end she her condition was still better than that recorded at baseline.&lt;br>
Patient #2 continued regular Enercel acupoint injection therapy and Enercel use. The clinical improvements he achieved during the 4 weeks of intensive treatment were maintained during the 3-month follow-up period. It appears that persistent acupoint injection therapy with Enercel may be required in order to maintain the initial positive effects.&lt;br>
&lt;strong>However, these findings are preliminary. Additional, formal studies and controlled clinical trials are required to expand and confirm these results.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="2003---treatment-of-als-with-chinese-medicine">2003 - Treatment of ALS with Chinese Medicine&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./treatment_of_als_with_chinese_medicine.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="practices-used-by-als-patient">Practices used by ALS patient.&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="new-zealand">New Zealand&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>South Auckland Chinese Medical Centre&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
Phone: 09 276 1183&lt;br>
Address: 271 Great South Road, Otahuhu, Auckland&lt;br>
Practitioner: Rong Helen Zhang&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>from &lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/non-drug-therapies/acupuncture/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ALS News Today&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>Carnitine</title><link>/alternative-treatment/carnitine/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/carnitine/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Acetyl-L-carnitine supplies L-carnitine, which is important in the transport of long chain fatty acids across mitochondrial membranes. In addition, the acetyl moiety can be transferred to provide acetyl CoA. Therefore, acetyl-L-carnitine improves cerebral oxidative energy production and fatty acid oxidation in muscles. It has shown beneficial effects in models of traumatic brain and spinal cord injury, cerebral ischemia, stroke and patients with Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease. In primary motor neuron cultures from rats, acetyl-L-carnitine was found to protect against kainate and NMDA-induced toxicity. In light of this, a randomized double blind placebo-controlled trial was performed in small number of patients with ALS to investigate the effects of add-on acetyl-L-carnitine to riluzole vs. riluzole only treatment. Patients tolerated the combination well and had a better score in the ALS Functional Rating Scale&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mechanisms2">Mechanisms:&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Enhanced exercise performance&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Reduced oxidative stress&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enhanced mitochondrial energy production&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Protection against excitotoxicity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Neurotrophic effects&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increased heat shock proteins&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;h4 id="2020---als-untangled-no-53-carnitine-supplementshttpswwwtandfonlinecomdoifull1010802167842120201726565">&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2020.1726565" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2020 - ALS Untangled No. 53: Carnitine Supplements&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./carnitine_supplements.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In conclusion, there are good theoretical mechanisms for carnitines, some pre-clinical evidence for LC and ALCAR, and a single clinical trial that suggested ALCAR could slow disease progression in PALS. All three carnitines appear to be well-tolerated, generally safe and inexpensive. We believe that there is a need for future clinical trials of carnitines in PALS to further elucidate their efficacy. Until there is further data, we cannot endorse any of these supplements as a definite way to slow ALS progression; &lt;strong>however, oral ALCAR at 1000mg three times daily (3000mg total daily dose) appears to be a theoretically promising supplement available for PALS whom would like to self-experiment&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="2013---randomised-double-blind-placebo-controlled-trial-of-acetyl-l-carnitine">2013 - Randomised double-blind placebo controlled trial of acetyl-L-carnitine&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./randomized_double_blinf_placebo_controller_trial_of_acetyl_l_carnitine_for_als.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Trial referenced in the ALS Untangle review&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="suggested-dose">Suggested Dose&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Acetyl-L-Carnitine: 1000mg three times daily (3000mg total daily dose)&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="natural-sources">Natural Sources&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Animal-based foods are good sources of carnitine, including:&lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Beef, 4 oz cooked - 56-162 mg&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Chicken, 4 oz cooked - 3-5 mg&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Milk, 1 cup whole - 8 mg&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cheese, 2 oz cheddar - 2 mg&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cheese, 2 oz cheddar - 2 mg&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="supplements">Supplements&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="consumerlab-acetyl-l-carnitine-product-review">Consumerlab acetyl-l-carnitine product review&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./consumerlab_acetyl-l-carnitine_supplement_review.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>excerpt from &lt;a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnins.2016.00611/full#B59">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnins.2016.00611/full#B59&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>excerpt from &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2020.1726565">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2020.1726565&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>excerpt from &lt;a href="https://www.webmd.com/vitamins-and-supplements/acetyl-l-carnitine-uses-risks#1-3">https://www.webmd.com/vitamins-and-supplements/acetyl-l-carnitine-uses-risks#1-3&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>Exercises</title><link>/alternative-treatment/exercises/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/exercises/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Exercise may have many benefits for ALS patients, including reducing depression and improving strength and stamina. But it must be performed carefully to be beneficial. Patients should work with a physical therapist to determine how best to exercise safely, as well as to ensure that they include stretching, strength-building, and range-of-motion exercises in their routine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Regular and moderate exercise is better than excessive exercise. It is important for patients to avoid overworking their muscles. Aching muscles after exercise mean that they have been overstressed, and this may actually speed muscle loss. Patients should stop exercising when they get tired, rather than trying to push through the fatigue.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="exercise-guildeline">Exercise Guildeline&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Aerobic exercise&lt;/strong> can increase muscle efficiency and endurance by increasing heart rate, respiratory rate and overall cardiovascular fitness. Aerobic exercise examples are &lt;strong>swimming&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>water walking&lt;/strong>, walking, cycling, rowing, &amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Remember to exercise in moderation - exercising to the point of fatigue may actually result in increased muscle weakness.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="stretching-exercises">Stretching exercises&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>May help decrease the frequency or intensity of muscle cramping. These should be done daily to prevent pain and stiffness.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="range-of-motion-exercises-rom">Range of motion exercises (ROM)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Help move the joints through their full range of motion. These should be performed actively, if possible, or passively if muscle weakness limits movement. These should be done daily to prevent pain and stiffness.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="strengthening-exercises">&lt;del>Strengthening exercises&lt;/del>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Are not recommended&lt;/strong>. Working out with weights will not strengthen those muscles already weakened by ALS and could result in increased muscle weakness.&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="2019---the-role-of-exercise-as-a-non-pharmacological-therapeutic-approach-for-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-beneficial-or-detrimentalhttpswwwncbinlmnihgovpmcarticlespmc6652799">&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6652799/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2019 - The Role of Exercise as a Non-pharmacological Therapeutic Approach for Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis: Beneficial or Detrimental?&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./als_role_of_exercise.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Although previous evidence suggests a potential relationship
between heavily active lifestyles and an increased incidence of
ALS (30, 31, 109), recent studies support that physical activity is
not necessarily a risk factor for ALS (42, 43, 110). There is now a
large body of evidence suggesting physical activity as a potential
therapeutic or even holistic approach for ALS.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="strengthening-exercises-may-slow-progression-of-alshttpswwwaancompressroomhomepressrelease516">&lt;a href="https://www.aan.com/PressRoom/home/PressRelease/516" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Strengthening Exercises May Slow Progression Of Als&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>The study found those who did moderate strengthening exercises had a 12-percent slower decrease in function and a 16-percent slower decline in quality of life over the six months than those who did the stretching exercises alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/als-and-exercise/">https://alsnewstoday.com/als-and-exercise/&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/16729-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-als">https://my.clevelandclinic.org/health/diseases/16729-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-als&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>MitoQ (coq10)</title><link>/alternative-treatment/coq10/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/coq10/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>MitoQ is an antioxidant. Its active ingredient is ubiquinone, as found in coenzyme Q10 and idebenone. However, the ubiquinone in MitoQ is attached to a positively charged, lipophilic molecule called TPP (triphenyl phosphonium), which allows it to selectively accumulate in mitochondria. This makes it more potent than untargeted ubiquinone analogs at protecting cells in culture from oxidative stress&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Oxidative stress is believed to play a major role in ALS pathogenesis&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. Unfortunately, trials of antioxidants have thus far failed to show any benefits in patients with ALS&lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> &lt;sup id="fnref:3">&lt;a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>. One explanation for these failures is that the antioxidants did not reach the optimal place. Since mitochondria are both the main producer and main target of oxidative stress, mitochondrial-focused antioxidant therapy might be more successful. Orally administered MitoQ can alter markers of both oxidative stress and mitochondrial dysfunction in cell culture&lt;sup id="fnref:4">&lt;a href="#fn:4" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">4&lt;/a>&lt;/sup> and animal model of ALS (11).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="2015---antioxidant-mitoq-shown-as-a-promising-therapy-for-alshttpsalsnewstodaycom20150716antioxidant-mitoq-shown-promising-therapy-als">&lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/2015/07/16/antioxidant-mitoq-shown-promising-therapy-als/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2015 - Antioxidant MitoQ Shown As A Promising Therapy for ALS&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./antioxidant_mitoq_shown_as_a_promising _therapy_for_als.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>“This study supports the role of mitochondrial dysfunction in the development and progression of ALS, which may allow
for the development of more mitochondria-targeted therapies to fight this disease,” concluded study’s co-author and
Director of the Center, Dr. Rafael Radi. “We also found that MitoQ has beneficial effects in the murine model of ALS,
which will likely lead to clinical trials using MitoQ with ALS patients and hopefully lead to extend the survival and
improve the quality of life of ALS patients.”&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="2015---an-overview-of-potential-targets-for-treating-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-and-huntingtons-diseasehttpswwwhindawicomjournalsbmri2015198612">&lt;a href="https://www.hindawi.com/journals/bmri/2015/198612/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2015 - An Overview of Potential Targets for Treating Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis and Huntington’s Disease&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./an_overview_of_potential_targets_for_treating_amyotrophic_lateral_sclerosis_and_huntingtons_disease.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>MitoQ is a mitochondrial antioxidant that contains the antioxidant Quinone linked to a lipophilic
triphenylphosphonium cation. Researchers showed that MitoQ prolonged life span and the pathology of SOD-knockout Drosophila melanogaster,
the enzyme involved in ALS. In addition, the compound has been shown to exert neuroprotective effects in SODG93A mice, slowing functional decline,
decreasing oxidative damage and disease progression, and increasing survival.&lt;br>
Furthermore, other studies showed that MitoQ preincubation prevented the cell death observed in cultures of motor
neurons + SOD-mutant astrocytes alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="2015---als-untangled-no-29-mitoqhttpswwwtandfonlinecomdoifull1031092167842120151050897">&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.3109/21678421.2015.1050897" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2015 - ALS Untangled No. 29: MitoQ&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./als_untangled_29_mitoq.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>MitoQ has a promising mechanism, positive preclinical data from two different ALS models, and appears reasonably safe
and inexpensive, especially at doses of 10 mg daily. Available anecdotal data are insufficient to determine how helpful
this might be in PALS. A small open-label pilot trial with validated ALS diagnoses and outcomes appears warranted.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Carri M, Valle C, Bozzo F, Cozzolino M.Oxidative stress and mitochondrial damage: importance in non-SOD1 ALS . Front Cell Neurosci. 2015;9:41.
&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0007&amp;amp;dbid=8&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=25741238" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PubMed&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0007&amp;amp;dbid=128&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=000349604900001" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Web of Science ®&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?hl=en&amp;amp;publication_year=2015&amp;amp;pages=41&amp;amp;author=M&amp;#43;Carri&amp;amp;author=C&amp;#43;Valle&amp;amp;author=F&amp;#43;Bozzo&amp;amp;author=M.&amp;#43;Cozzolino&amp;amp;title=Oxidative&amp;#43;stress&amp;#43;and&amp;#43;mitochondrial&amp;#43;damage%3A&amp;#43;importance&amp;#43;in&amp;#43;non-SOD1&amp;#43;ALS" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Scholar&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Kaufmann P, Thompson J, Buchsbaum R, Shefner J, Krivickas L, Katz J, et al.Phase II trial of coq10 for ALS finds insufficient evidence to justify phase III. Ann Neurol. 2009;66:234–44.
&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0008&amp;amp;dbid=16&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=10.1002%2Fana.21743" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Crossref&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0008&amp;amp;dbid=128&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=000269845400017" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Web of Science ®&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?hl=en&amp;amp;publication_year=2009&amp;amp;pages=234-44&amp;amp;author=P&amp;#43;Kaufmann&amp;amp;author=J&amp;#43;Thompson&amp;amp;author=R&amp;#43;Buchsbaum&amp;amp;author=J&amp;#43;Shefner&amp;amp;author=L&amp;#43;Krivickas&amp;amp;author=J&amp;#43;Katz&amp;amp;title=Phase&amp;#43;II&amp;#43;trial&amp;#43;of&amp;#43;coq10&amp;#43;for&amp;#43;ALS&amp;#43;finds&amp;#43;insufficient&amp;#43;evidence&amp;#43;to&amp;#43;justify&amp;#43;phase&amp;#43;III" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Scholar&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Graf M, Ecker D, Horowski R, Kramer B, Riederer P, Gerlach M, et al.High dose vitamin E therapy in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis as add-on therapy to riluzole: results of a placebo controlled double-blind study. J Neural Transm. 2005;112:646–60.
&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0009&amp;amp;dbid=16&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=10.1007%2Fs00702-004-0220-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Crossref&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0009&amp;amp;dbid=128&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=000229439700005" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Web of Science ®&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?hl=en&amp;amp;publication_year=2005&amp;amp;pages=646-60&amp;amp;author=M&amp;#43;Graf&amp;amp;author=D&amp;#43;Ecker&amp;amp;author=R&amp;#43;Horowski&amp;amp;author=B&amp;#43;Kramer&amp;amp;author=P&amp;#43;Riederer&amp;amp;author=M&amp;#43;Gerlach&amp;amp;title=High&amp;#43;dose&amp;#43;vitamin&amp;#43;E&amp;#43;therapy&amp;#43;in&amp;#43;amyotrophic&amp;#43;lateral&amp;#43;sclerosis&amp;#43;as&amp;#43;add-on&amp;#43;therapy&amp;#43;to&amp;#43;riluzole%3A&amp;#43;results&amp;#43;of&amp;#43;a&amp;#43;placebo&amp;#43;controlled&amp;#43;double-blind&amp;#43;study." target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Scholar&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>Cassina P, Cassina A, Pehar M, Castellanos R, Gandelman M, de Leon A, et al.Journal Neurosci. 2008;16:4115–22.
&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0010&amp;amp;dbid=16&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=10.1523%2FJNEUROSCI.5308-07.2008" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Crossref&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/servlet/linkout?suffix=CIT0010&amp;amp;dbid=128&amp;amp;doi=10.3109%2F21678421.2015.1050897&amp;amp;key=000255012500004" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Web of Science ®&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;amp;q=Cassina&amp;#43;P%2C&amp;#43;Cassina&amp;#43;A%2C&amp;#43;Pehar&amp;#43;M%2C&amp;#43;Castellanos&amp;#43;R%2C&amp;#43;Gandelman&amp;#43;M%2C&amp;#43;de&amp;#43;Leon&amp;#43;A%2C&amp;#43;et&amp;#43;al.Journal&amp;#43;Neurosci.&amp;#43;2008%3B16%3A4115%E2%80%9322." target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google Scholar&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:4" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>NAD</title><link>/alternative-treatment/nad-precursors/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/nad-precursors/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="what-is-nad">What is NAD&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NAD) is a cofactor central to metabolism. Found in all living cells, NAD is called a dinucleotide because it consists of two nucleotides joined through their phosphate groups. One nucleotide contains an adenine nucleobase and the other nicotinamide. NAD exists in two forms: an oxidized and reduced form, abbreviated as NAD+ and NADH respectively.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[&amp;hellip;]There are three major functions of NAD. First, it allows us to convert our food into ATP, which is the biological chemical currency that allows us to move our muscles, have ideas, and run all of our cells. Second, NAD also catalyzes conversion of the food we eat into everything we are, including DNA, RNA, proteins, hormones and lipids. Third, NAD helps us to repair cellular damage to DNA, protein and fat that is caused by the way we live our lives, what we eat or drink, how we sleep, travel, sun, the air we breath, stress and just plain old wear-and-tear. &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-are-nmn-na-and-nr">What are NMN, NA and NR?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Nicotinamide or Niacinamide (NAM)
Nicotinamide mononucleotide (NMN)
Nicotinic Acid or Niacin (NA)&lt;br>
NR (Nicotinamide Riboside)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>are all precursors of NAD&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="nr">NR&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Patented by ChromaDex, sold under TruNiagen. Could also be found in Elysium Health &amp;lsquo;Basis&amp;rsquo; product though manufacturer is unknown at the time of writing.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h4 id="evaluation-of-the-nad-biosynthetic-pathway-in-als-patients-and-effect-of-modulating-nad-levels-in-hsod1-linked-als-mouse-modelshttpswwwsciencedirectcomsciencearticlepiis0014488620300509via3dihub">&lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0014488620300509?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Evaluation of the NAD+ biosynthetic pathway in ALS patients and effect of modulating NAD+ levels in hSOD1-linked ALS mouse models&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./evalutaion_of_the_nad+_biosynthetic_pathways_in_als_patient.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="eh301---nr--pt-pterostilbene">EH301 - NR + PT (pterostilbene)&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>19 Feb 2019&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.trialsitenews.com/university-of-valencia-research-reveals-that-eh301-may-halt-als-progression/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Valencia Research Reveals that eH301 May Halt ALS Progression&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>18 Feb 2019
&lt;a href="https://www.alzforum.org/news/research-news/small-trial-eh301-appears-halt-progression-als" target="_blank" rel="noopener">In Small Trial, EH301 Appears to Halt Progression of ALS&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>PDF - Jan 2019&lt;/strong>
&lt;a href="./eh301_study.pdf">Efficacy and tolerability of EH301 for amyotrophic lateral sclerosis: a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled human pilot study&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>3 Apr 2018
&lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/2018/04/03/eh301-granted-orphan-drug-designation-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Elysium Health’s EH301 Designated Orphan Drug by FDA for Treatment of ALS&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="nmn">NMN&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="nmn-as-a-potential-therapeutic-agent-for-muscle-diseasehttpswwwnmncomnewsnmn-as-potential-therapeutic-agent-for-muscle-disease">&lt;a href="https://www.nmn.com/news/nmn-as-potential-therapeutic-agent-for-muscle-disease" target="_blank" rel="noopener">NMN as a potential therapeutic agent for muscle disease&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;h4 id="enhancing-nad-salvage-pathway-reverts-the-toxicity-of-primary-astrocytes-expressing-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-linked-mutant-superoxide-dismutase-1-sod1httpswwwncbinlmnihgovpubmed27002158">&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27002158" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Enhancing NAD+ Salvage Pathway Reverts the Toxicity of Primary Astrocytes Expressing Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis-linked Mutant Superoxide Dismutase 1 (SOD1)&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicotinamide_adenine_dinucleotide">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nicotinamide_adenine_dinucleotide&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.foodmatterslive.com/news-and-comment/news/chromadex-nad">https://www.foodmatterslive.com/news-and-comment/news/chromadex-nad&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>Theracurmin</title><link>/alternative-treatment/theracurmin/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/theracurmin/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Curcumin has been shown to produce neuroprotective effects. It’s a compound in turmeric (a member of the ginger family), which is often used in the diet and medicines of Southeast Asia, China, and India.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Curcumin is able to cross the blood brain barrier (BBB) — a highly selective membrane that shields the central nervous system from general blood circulation — which makes it an ideal therapeutic candidate for diseases of the central nervous system (brain and spinal cord), such as Alzheimer’s disease, multiple sclerosis, and Parkinson’s disease.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Theracurmin (nanocurmin) is a more bio aaialable version of normal curcumin supplements.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="mechanisms1">Mechanisms:&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>decrease neuroinflammation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>prevent oxidative stress&lt;/li>
&lt;li>might inhibit protein aggregation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>alter fecal microbiome&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h4 id="2018---als-untangled-44---curcuminhttpswwwtandfonlinecomdoifull1010802167842120181440738">&lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2018.1440738" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2018 - ALS Untangled 44 - Curcumin&lt;/a>&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./als_untangled_44_curcumin.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Oral curcumin is safe, inexpensive, and has at least four potential mechanisms by which it might theoretically be useful in treating PALS. Flawed preclinical studies showed benefits of a curcumin chemical analog in a cell model of ALS, three PALS experienced validated motor improvements on regimens including curcumin (although there are several alternative explanations for these improvements) and there is one small pilot trial showing some benefit of curcumin in PALS. Based on the evidence presented in this review, some of us are planning a trial of Theracurmin at 90 mg twice daily in PALS.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h2 id="supplements">Supplements&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Theracurmin&lt;/strong>&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0765DHTVL/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=alsmnd-20&amp;amp;camp=1789&amp;amp;creative=9325&amp;amp;linkCode=as2&amp;amp;creativeASIN=B0765DHTVL&amp;amp;linkId=1fd73afdf55d78d45d58d0ac32178413" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Buy on Amazon&lt;/a>&lt;br>
Dosage: 90mg with breakfast, 90mg with diner&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>excerpt from &lt;a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2018.1440738">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/21678421.2018.1440738&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item><item><title>Vitamin B-12</title><link>/alternative-treatment/vitamin-b12/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/vitamin-b12/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="high-dose-vitamin-b12-may-improve-als-prognosis-if-started-early-study-suggestshttpsalsnewstodaycom20190117high-dose-vitamin-b12-helpful-early-diagnosis">&lt;a href="https://alsnewstoday.com/2019/01/17/high-dose-vitamin-b12-helpful-early-diagnosis/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">High-dose Vitamin B12 May Improve ALS Prognosis if Started Early, Study Suggests&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In conclusion, ultra-high-dose methylcobalamin was not found to be significantly superior to placebo. However, ultra-high-dose methylcobalamin therapy may improve the prognosis of patients with ALS, if administered early in the disease course,&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="ultra-high-dose-methylcobalamin-in-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-a-long-term-phase-iiiii-randomised-controlled-study">Ultra-high-dose methylcobalamin in amyotrophic lateral sclerosis: a long-term phase II/III randomised controlled study&lt;/h3></description></item></channel></rss>