<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>protocols | ALS | MND</title><link>/tag/protocols/</link><atom:link href="/tag/protocols/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>protocols</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url><title>protocols</title><link>/tag/protocols/</link></image><item><title>Patricia Kane Protocol</title><link>/alternative-treatment/patricia-kane-protocol/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/patricia-kane-protocol/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Protocols for ALS are mainly empirical (i.e based on personal experience),
so please be sure to always do your research and make your own mind.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Whals Protocol</title><link>/alternative-treatment/whals-protocol/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/whals-protocol/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Protocols for ALS are mainly empirical (i.e based on personal experience),
so please be sure to always do your research and make your own mind.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Deanna Protocol</title><link>/alternative-treatment/deanna-protocol/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/alternative-treatment/deanna-protocol/</guid><description>&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
Protocols for ALS are mainly empirical (i.e based on personal experience),
so please be sure to always do your research and make your own mind.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="the-story-behind-the-protocol">The story behind the protocol&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In 2009, Deanna was a healthy 31-yr-old pregnant newlywed with plenty of energy, an active lifestyle, and a successful career as a trial attorney and a Partner in a Tampa law firm. Her life came to a halt, when she was diagnosed with ALS after she found herself falling and losing balance frequently. She sought help from the most credible physicians and institutions in the country in treating ALS and they all told her the same thing: “There is no cure. There is no effective way to manage the disease. Your disease is progressing quickly and you will be dead in 2 years.” They were right. Within months, she went from walking normally and running several miles a day to walking very slowly with a cane. She was dying…quickly. This is when Deanna’s father Dr. Tedone (MD) took action.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He began reading all scientific research on ALS in the past 100 years to try to find a solution for Deanna. Based on his medical knowledge and familiarity with ALS research, he began testing safe substances on Deanna and eventually teamed up with scientists at the University of South Florida to test and refine these substances in the lab. This is how the original Deanna Protocol was born. When on the Deanna Protocol, Deanna’s physical condition stopped deteriorating and she stabilized (which is unheard of in ALS patients who are progressing quickly). Deanna was doing so well on the Deanna Protocol that other ALS patients who knew her began asking Dr. Tedone to share information with them on what Deanna was taking. Others with ALS began seeing incredible results and began referring friends and writing about their improvements on ALS related blogs and websites. Word of mouth continued to spread and, now, there are over 6,000 individuals with ALS on the Deanna Protocol worldwide.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Throughout the years, Dr. Tedone and scientists at different universities have tested and improved upon the Protocol, which has given way to the Deanna Protocol that exists today: a patent pending substance with a proprietary ratio of &lt;strong>Arginine (AAKG)&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>Alpha-Ketoglutaric acid (AKG)&lt;/strong>, and &lt;strong>Gamma-Aminobutyric acid (GABA)&lt;/strong>. These are all substances that are naturally found in the body. However, people with ALS need more of these substances to give fuel to the Krebs Cycle (energy producing cycle) in their nerve cells, in order to keep their diseased nerve cells alive. Think of the Deanna Protocol as special fuel needed to keep the cell’s engine running when the engine is malfunctioning because of a disease.&lt;sup id="fnref:1">&lt;a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find a lot more information on the official website: &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/">https://winningthefight.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-protocol">The protocol&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="supplements">Supplements&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="arginine-alpha-ketoglutarate-aakg">Arginine-alpha-ketoglutarate (AAKG)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="gamma-aminobutyric-acid-gaba">Gamma Aminobutyric Acid (GABA)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="optional-supplements">Optional Supplements&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="alpha-ketoglutarate-akg">Alpha-ketoglutarate (AKG)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="coenzyme-q10-coq10">Coenzyme Q10 (CoQ10)&lt;/h4>
&lt;p>TODO&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dr-tedone-advices">Dr Tedone advices&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Take AAKG with a ration of 1:1 Arginine to Alpha-Ktoglutarate.&lt;br>
Example:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://nz.iherb.com/pr/Primaforce-AAKG-Unflavored-250-g/58649" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Primaforce&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.simplesanutrition.com/products/aakg-powder-250-grams.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Simplesa&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="borrelia-bacteria">Borrelia Bacteria&lt;/h2>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>We have a strong body of evidence suggesting that ALS is likely caused by an undiagnosed infection with borrelia bacteria and at times coinfections Deanna and the vast majority of other individuals we have worked with who have ALS have been diagnosed with borrelia infections &lt;sup id="fnref:2">&lt;a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2&lt;/a>&lt;/sup>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A full page on the idea &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/portfolio-items/does-bacteria-cause-neurological-diseases/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Does Bacteria Cause Neurological Diseases&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/pulsed-method/deanna-is-on-the-pulsed-method/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How Deanna is treated&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Please check &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/borrelia-bacteria/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this page&lt;/a> with test recommendation&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="science">Science&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Arginine-alpha-ketoglutarate (AAKG)
Delivers energy to nerves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Alpha-ketoglutarate (AKG)
Delivers energy to nerves&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gamma Aminobutyric Acid (GABA)
Inhibitory neurotransmitter&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nicotinamide
Stops nerve cell death&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="articles">Articles&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="alert alert-note">
&lt;div>
The titles of the articles are clickable and will redirect you to the online resource.
The quote is the conclusion or an extract of the article.
Please be sure to read them fully
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h3 id="2017---evaluation-of-holistic-treatment-for-als-reveals-possible-mechanism-and-therapeutic-potentialhttpswwwncbinlmnihgovpmcarticlespmc6326589">&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6326589/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2017 - Evaluation of Holistic Treatment for ALS Reveals Possible Mechanism and Therapeutic Potential&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./evaluation_of_holistic_treatment_for_als_reveals_possible_mechanism_and_therapeutic_potential.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>In this study, glutamate exposure to human motoneurons was investigated and found not to significantly affect cell viability or electrophysiological properties. However, varicosities were observed in axons suggestive of transport impairment that was dose dependent for glutamate exposure. Surprisingly, a subset of the components of the DP eliminated these varicosities.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2014---metabolic-therapy-with-deanna-protocol-supplementation-delays-disease-progression-and-extends-survival-in-amyotrophic-lateral-sclerosis-als-mouse-modelhttpswwwncbinlmnihgovpmcarticlespmc4111621">&lt;a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4111621/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2014 - Metabolic Therapy with Deanna Protocol Supplementation Delays Disease Progression and Extends Survival in Amyotrophic Lateral Sclerosis (ALS) Mouse Model&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./deanna_protocol_delay.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Our results support the idea that targeted metabolic therapies, like the DP, can improve motor function and survival time, though further research is needed to elucidate the cellular and molecular mechanisms underlying these results. Dose response studies, histological analysis, and metabolomic analysis will help to define the optimal formula to enhance metabolic substrate delivery and utilization to help mitigate the ALS pathology. The components of the DP supplement have a good safety profile and are readily available over the counter, which is an important consideration in moving this therapy into phase I clinical trial.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h3 id="2013---als-untangled---deanna-protocolhttpswwwalsuntangledcomreviewdeanna-protocol">&lt;a href="https://www.alsuntangled.com/review/deanna-protocol/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2013 - ALS Untangled - Deanna Protocol&lt;/a>&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="btn btn-outline-primary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="./als_untangled_20_deanna_protocol.pdf">Download PDF&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Mitochondrial dysfunction, glutamate excitotoxicity, and oxidative stress have all been implicated in ALS pathogenesis, and targeting these mechanisms individually or by a cocktail such as the Deanna Protocol could play a role in future ALS therapies. However, many of the preclinical and animal studies related to these pathways have not translated into successful treatments in patients with ALS. While there are anecdotal reports of improvements in patients with ALS on the Deanna Protocol, there is no convincing objective evidence of benefit yet. Thus, at this time, ALSUntangled does not recommend the Deanna Protocol to patients with ALS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before it can be recommended, a reproducible version of the Deanna Protocol should be shown to influence plausible physiologic mechanisms such as central nervous system ketone bodies, as well as clinically meaningful outcome measures such as ALSFRS-R and FVC in patients with ALS.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;section class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
&lt;hr>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>from &lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">winningthefight.org&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://winningthefight.org/borrelia-bacteria/">https://winningthefight.org/borrelia-bacteria/&lt;/a> &lt;a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/section></description></item></channel></rss>